Hi, my name is Tarun,
and I'm from
the camera software team.
In this video, I'll cover the new
camera features
on iPhone Duo,
and I'll go over how to build
a great experience with them.
I'll begin by introducing
the new front cameras
on iPhone Duo.
Then I'll share how to handle
camera direction changes
when people open
or close their device.
Finally, I'll cover some tips
that will polish your app's
camera preview on iPhone Duo.
Now, it's time to meet
the iPhone Duo's
new front cameras.
iPhone Duo is the first iPhone
to support two front cameras.
Both of these cameras
are square sensors
with an ultrawide field of view.
On the outside of the device,
you'll find the outer
ultrawide camera.
It takes fantastic photos
and videos.
Open the device
and you'll find
the inner ultrawide camera,
the first under-display camera
on iPhone.
Your app can stream
from the front cameras
through AVFoundation.
Just like on any other iPhone,
use the discovery session
AVCaptureDeviceDiscoverySession
to find the front camera.
Request position .front,
along with the Wide
or Ultra Wide device type.
When you do this on iPhone Duo,
your app will now discover
the new Virtual Front Camera.
The Virtual Front Camera is a new
AVCaptureDevice that automatically
switches between the outer
and inner physical cameras.
When you have your iPhone Duo open,
the Virtual Front Camera uses
the front camera
on the inner display.
When you close your iPhone,
the camera will automatically switch
to the front camera
on the outer display.
The Virtual Front Camera uses
the most relevant front camera
for your app.
The Virtual Front Camera
handles the camera switch for you.
But you can do even more
by responding to
camera direction changes.
On iPhone Duo,
each front camera
has its own AVCaptureDevice type.
Use the built-in outer ultrawide
device type to access the front camera
on the outer display.
Use the built-in inner ultrawide
device type to access the one
on the inner display.
When you use these device types,
you get access to full capabilities
of each camera.
The inner ultrawide camera has 1080p
video resolution with support
up to 60fps.
The outer ultrawide camera supports
up to 4K resolution and 120fps.
When your app uses
the virtual front camera,
you only have access to features
common across both physical cameras.
That is a max 1080p resolution
and 60fps.
It's also important to note that depth
is only supported
when accessing individual cameras.
When you use individual cameras,
your app is responsible for switching
between them
when someone opens
or closes their iPhone Duo.
Use the new
AVCaptureDeviceDirectionCoordinator
API to manage the transition.
For some background, AVCaptureDevice
has always provided
a fixed position property.
On iPhone, that has always been
back or front.
Both the inner and outer front cameras
have the value front.
But things get more interesting
on iPhone Duo,
where displays can face
opposite directions.
This would mean a front camera
is not always looking at you.
For example, you could be looking
at the inner display,
but be streaming
from the outer front camera.
In this case, a front camera
is facing away from you.
And while your app is streaming
from the outer front camera,
you might close the device.
That same camera now swings
to directly face you.
If you flip the device
while it's open,
you can take a selfie
with the back cameras.
Now your app and the back camera
are both directly facing you.
To ensure your app always knows
where the cameras are facing,
use the direction coordinator.
The direction coordinator
tells your app where the cameras are
and keeps you up to date
as that changes.
To create a direction coordinator,
you need three things:
your app's UIView,
the device types you want to monitor,
and a change handler.
When your app's UIView
is on the outer display,
the coordinator will show
outer display front cameras
as forward-facing,
and the rear cameras
as backward-facing.
When the device is opened,
your app's UIView
moves to the inner display.
Your change handler will be called
and will report the outer front
and rear cameras
as backward-facing cameras,
and the inner front camera
as forward-facing.
If you flip the device
while it's open,
you can move a camera app
to the outer display.
When this happens, you'll find
the rear and outer front camera
both become
forward-facing devices.
On iPhone Duo, a camera app
can use both displays at once.
That's great for a group video call,
or for showing a child something fun
while you take their photo.
In this situation, you will have
two different UIViews for each display
at the same time.
One for the outer display
and one for the inner display.
Create a separate direction
coordinator for each view.
The outer display's coordinator
will report the rear cameras
as forward-facing,
while the inner display's coordinator
will report them as backward-facing.
Each coordinator reports positions
relative to its own view.
Camera apps can enable this
using the SceneAccessories API.
Learn how in the video,
"Leverage multiple displays
and scenes on iPhone Duo."
Because the direction coordinator
is tied to a view,
it is isolated to the main actor.
Keep in mind that your change handler
from the direction coordinator
should not use
AVFoundation APIs directly.
Rather than handing you
an AVCaptureDevice, the coordinator
provides an AVCaptureDeviceDescriptor.
The device descriptor is
a main-actor-safe, sendable
representation of an AVCaptureDevice.
It contains all the
information needed
to create an AVCaptureDevice
and can be safely passed
to your camera actor.
From there, you can interact
with your AVFoundation APIs.
Here's what you should do
in your change handler.
As someone opens or closes
their device,
your change handler will be called
to tell your app
which camera is now forward-facing.
At this time, reconfigure your
AVCaptureSession to keep streaming
from the forward-facing camera.
Consider how the new camera direction
affects your decision
to mirror the preview.
When the rear camera
is forward-facing,
mirror the preview
for a natural selfie
camera experience.
Finally, use the change handler
to perform any UI updates
while changing cameras.
You'll find the direction coordinator
in AVKit.
More details about the coordinator
can be found in the article,
"Choosing a Camera
by the Direction it Faces"
in Apple's Developer Documentation.
Now that we've gone over
camera direction changes,
I'll go over some tips
to give your app a polished preview
on iPhone Duo.
When you stream using
the full field of view
of rear camera on inner display,
you will have additional display space
around your preview.
Take advantage of this extra space
by offsetting the preview,
so you can group controls
in the remaining space.
Alternatively, you can have
the preview fill the display.
You have the flexibility
to make the decision
that's right for your app.
Use the videoGravity property
on AVCaptureVideoPreviewLayer
to determine how to lay out
your preview
within the layer bounds.
Check out the documentation
for more details.
When streaming from
the ultrawide front cameras,
you can fill the display
by taking advantage
of the square sensor.
Use dynamicAspectRatio
on AVCaptureDevice
to select a landscape aspect ratio
on the inner display.
Learn more about the power
of the square sensor in the video
"Support the Center Stage
Front Camera in your iOS app"
from WWDC26.
A final note on handling rotation
in your app:
Adopt the rotation coordinator
to ensure your camera preview
and photos always remain upright.
On iPhone Duo, the rotation
coordinator will update
when your app moves displays.
Use the coordinator to ensure
your app's rotation
is applied consistently
across displays.
Read the article
"Supporting Device Rotation
in Your Camera App"
for more information about using
the rotation coordinator.
After adopting
the rotation coordinator,
disable camera-sensor-orientation
compensation to improve performance.
This compensation is enabled
on all the front cameras
on iPhone Duo.
A few next steps.
Use the iOS 27.1 SDK
to take full advantage
of iPhone Duo.
Decide how your app will handle
switching cameras
when the device opens or closes.
Adopt a direction coordinator
if you want to move beyond
the virtual front camera.
Finally, test your app on iPhone Duo
and make sure
your camera preview looks great.
I look forward to how your camera app
unfolds on iPhone Duo.